Guide to the University Christian Movement Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
University Christian Movement Records
1955-1995
1966-1969
RG 235
Yale University Divinity School Library
20
(49 boxes)
The University Christian Movement was an ecumenical student Christian organization in the USA that existed between the years 1966-1969. The UCM was the successor to the National Student Christian Federation. It was the U.S.A. member of the World Student Christian Federation and a related movement of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA. UCM sought to be a student movement that would unite the academic community through social action. The organization dissolved in 1969 due to a lack of program direction and an inability to define itself.
University Christian Movement (United States)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Princeton Theological Seminary Library, 2010
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other collections related to the University Christian Movement that can be found at Yale Divinity School Library:
National Student Christian Federation Records
Biographical / Historical
The University Christian Movement (UCM) was an ecumenical student Christian organization in the United States of America that existed between the years 1966-1969. The UCM was the successor to the National Student Christian Federation (NSCF). UCM was the U.S.A. member of the World Student Christian Federation and a related movement of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA. UCM sought to be a student movement that would unite the academic community through social action. It was very much an organization of its time, and the material produced by the UCM reflects the enthusiasm and ideology for activism, as well as the societal anxiety caused by the Vietnam War in the late 1960s.
The UCM was created to address problems within the NSCF, as the NSCF's organizational framework was not accommodating the wants and needs of the students it served. As the 1960s progressed, students became more active in political and social concerns. At the annual meeting in September of 1966, the NSCF voted to reorganize under the name the University Christian Movement. UCM wished to be an organization where people at the national level could serve as resource liaisons for grass roots activists on the regional and local levels. Unlike its predecessor, the UCM did not restrict membership to Protestant organizations and included Roman Catholic and Orthodox organizations as members. The UCM also accepted secular organizations as related organizations, such as the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS).
The organizational structure of the UCM included an Annual Assembly in which important matters were discussed and voted upon. The Annual Assembly also voted for members of the General Committee, which consisted of forty-five people elected by the Assembly and officers of all UCM committees who met twice a year to approve or reject policy, personnel, program, and finance matters. The Standing Committees of the General Committee conducted administrative affairs such as policy, finance, and long term program planning and evaluation, while the Program Committees dealt with immediate concerns. The Standing Committees were a) Program Planning and Evaluation, b) Nominations, c) Personnel, d) Finance, and e) Membership. The Program Committees were the a) Committee on Study Resources and Publications, b) Committee on International Ecumenical Ministries, c) Field Services Committee, d) Political Concerns Committee, e) Committee on Theological Reflection, and f) any task force that needed to be created for an issue. In addition to the Standing and Program Committees, an Advisory Council was formed to give voice but no voting power to the "Committee of National Staff of the NCCUSA Department of Higher Education, mission boards, Christian social action boards, departments of ministry, councils of churches, the Ecumenical Voluntary Service Center, other boards or agencies concerned with higher education," (UCM Articles of Operation). The concerns of the groups could be heard, but ultimately power rested with the students.
The program departments of the UCM illustrate the organization's commitment to social and political activism. The Field Department of the UCM was its most effective program department. This department was the last holdover from the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions. While the SVM Field Department sent traveling secretaries to universities and colleges to promote missions abroad for Protestant mission boards and agencies, the UCM Field Department supported individuals who were involved in local social and political programs. Several of the Field Staff were involved in SDS projects, such as Steve Johnson, who worked on the Radical Education Project in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Another holdover from the SVM was the Quadrennial conference, and the Process '67 conference can be viewed as the last Quadrennial. Compared to past conferences, Process '67 was much more unstructured in organization and form. UCM centered the conference on Depth Education Groups (DEGs). These small groups were designed to concentrate on a single issue and find new ways to confront that issue through education, strategy, and model building. DEGs were conducted on a variety of social and political topics such as White Power and the Exploitation of the Ghetto; Abortion; and Mass Media, Public Opinion, and Politics. Process '67 also employed closed circuit television in the hotel to broadcast conference events and talks, conducted workshops on the arts, held worship services, and coordinated a film festival.
At the General Committee meeting on March 1, 1969, the UCM voted to dissolve. UCM had spent three years struggling to find a clear identity and let all voices and perspectives be heard within the organization. Without a clear, defining principle the UCM could not bring unity to the diverse perspectives within the organization. Instead there were different groups vying for attention and funding. UCM also had a sustainability problem as its elected officers cycled off each year, resulting in a new direction that did not address follow up for past programs and activities. Without consistent leadership and identity the UCM could not be maintained.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, position papers, news clippings, reports, and various publications detailing the administrative and program activities of the University Christian Movement.
Series 1: The UCM Administrative Records series is divided into nine subseries. The General Committee records illustrate the organization grappling with identity and program direction. The Advisory Council shows the perspective of those in the NCCCUSA Department of Higher Education and agency and mission boards on the UCM. The Officers meeting records contain minutes and materials for reading prior to meeting attendance. The Administrative Correspondence subseries contains correspondence ranging from general to that of the last UCM president Nell Sale. The Budget and Finance Committee subseries comprises budgets and meeting minutes. The Membership Committee contains applications to join UCM, correspondence, and meeting minutes. The Program and Planning Evaluation Committee contains meeting minutes and reports regarding programing. The Personnel Committee includes correspondence, job descriptions for UCM positions, and meeting minutes. The Nominations Committee consists of recommendations and nominations to the General Committee and for the election of officers.
Series 2: The UCM Program Records series is divided into six subseries. The Field Service Committee records contain both the administrative records for the department and the correspondence and reports from field staff. The Political Concerns Committee houses a variety of topical material on UCM political interests as well as correspondence, minutes, and reports. The Caucuses and Task Forces subseries comprises meeting minutes and reports from the various groups including the Black Caucus, Ideology Task Force, Latin America Task Force, Radical Caucus, and the Southern Africa Task Force. The Committee on International Ecumenical Ministry includes proposals, meeting minutes, and reports on groups working with international students on college campuses. The Committee on Study Resources and Publications contains correspondence, drafts of publications, meeting minutes, and materials relating to UCM creation and history. The Theological Reflection Committee includes meeting minutes and memos on theological issues within the UCM.
Series 3: The Publications series comprises the various printed material produced and/or distributed by the UCM. The Second Look newsletter and The Wind and Chaff journal were the two primary publications produced by the University Christian Movement.
Series 4: The Conference series is divided into three subseries. The first subseries details the program coordinating, meeting minutes, and reports for the UCM Annual Assemblies. The second subseries contains correspondence, evaluations, meeting minutes, promotion materials, program coordination, and a scrapbook describing the Process '67 conference. The Other Conferences subseries are divided into two subseries: UCM Conferences and Other Conferences. The UCM Conferences consists of planning materials for various seminars, and preparation materials for the WSCF Turku '68 conference. The Other Conferences subseries contains correspondence and planning material for the Church and Society Conference sponsored by the National Churches in Christ in the USA.
Series 5: The Organizations series is divided into four subseries. The Member Organizations subseries contain correspondence, program materials, and reports from UCM member groups. The World Student Christian Federation subseries consists of correspondence, meeting minutes, papers, and reports from various activities. The Related Organizations subseries includes correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports from the National Council of Churches Department of Higher Education and Ecumenical Voluntary Service Committee, the Students for a Democratic Society, and the YMCA. The Other Organizations subseries contains subject files on organizations not specifically related to UCM.
Series 6: The Collected Materials series is divided into two subseries: The William G. Roy Research Files and The Paul E. Schrading Papers. William G. Roy was the Southeast regional president for the UCM in 1968 while attending Emory University. While attending graduate school at the University of Michigan, he wrote a sociology paper on the UCM. The Roy subseries contains his research notes and notations on UCM materials. The correspondence files are a mix of Roy's own correspondence, as well as UCM correspondence that includes his notes. Paul E. Schrading was the Associate General Secretary in 1966 and took over as General Secretary in 1968. The Schrading subseries contains a mix of topical news clippings, meeting minutes, reports, photographs, and papers such as Alphabet Soup, the Sixties, and Process '67, as well as a draft of Schrading's remembrance of UCM that was printed in the Journal of Ecumenical Studies.
Arrangement
I. General Committee and Standing Committee Records
II. Program Records
III. Publications
IV. Conferences
V. Organizations
VI. Collected Material
Universities and colleges -- Religion; Youth in the ecumenical movement
- Administrative Records, Series I
  - General Committee
    - Call to Consultation, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Bunch, Charlotte, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, General, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Inquiries, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, General, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and memos re. future of Motive magazine, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Sale, Nell, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence re. UCM office space and possible relocation, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re. UCM dissolution, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Depth Education Group reports and materials re. racism, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Directory and contact lists, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Drafts of meeting minutes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Drafts of meeting minutes re. UCM dissolution, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Faculty re. creating a Faculty caucus, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Meeting materials and notes of Paul Schrading, 1968 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meeting materials includes drafts of meeting minutes, 1968 October-November (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Meeting materials, preparatory papers on UCM Ideology, notes of Paul Schrading, 1969 February (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Meeting minutes, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Meeting minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Meeting minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Memos from Jay Jones (UCM western region vice-president), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - News clippings re. UCM dissolution, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes of Paul Schrading, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Organizing Principle, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Preparatory meeting materials including notes and reports from committees or projects, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Preparatory meeting materials, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Reports, How Radical is the University Christian Movement: a Critique by Mark Juergensmeyer, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Responses to the UCM dissolution, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Stimulator papers including The Church as a Social Pioneer by H. Richard Niebuhr and Some Thoughts on Movement, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Strategy meeting on Direction of UCM: Correspondence, papers, and meeting minutes, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Strategy meeting on Direction of UCM: Correspondence, memos, notes, and papers, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - USCC-NSCF-UCM succession, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Working file of Nell Sale (UCM President). Includes notes, budget information, memos, and reports, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Working file of Nell Sale (UCM President). Includes correspondence, memos, notes, and reports., 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Advisory Council
    - Correspondence, General, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence re. meeting attendance, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence re. meeting attendance, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence and meeting minutes of Richard Tappan (Chairman of UCM Advisory Council), 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Executive Committee of Advisory Council: Correspondence, memos, and minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Mailing lists, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Meeting minutes, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Memos including preparatory materials for meetings, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Memos of M.O. Williams, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Officers' Meetings Records
    - Correspondence re. meeting location includes Len Clough's notes, 1966 October (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Materials for meeting, 1967 Setember 7-12 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Materials for meeting, 1967 December (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Materials for and submitted to May meeting, 1968 May (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Meeting minutes includes drafts, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Memos, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Speeches made by officers, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Administrative Correspondence
    - McIntire, Carl Thomas, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - re. historical material, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - re. location options for conferences and meetings, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Requests for information, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Requests for information, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - re. African Students Conference, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Chickering, Sherman, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Annual assembly, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence of Nell Sale (UCM President). Include carbon copies from UCM staff., 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence of Nell Sale (UCM President). Includes carbon copies from other UCM staff., 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - re. University of the Suburbs project, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Budget and Finance Committee
    - Correspondence re. Tax exemption and incorporation of UCM, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Budget information for 1967, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Meeting minutes, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Membership Committee
    - Applications submitted, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Contact list, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Correspondence of Richard Van Voorhis, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Information re. membership application to the UCM, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Meetings minutes and reports, 1966, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Memos, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Working file of Henry Bucher (Secretary of Field Department), 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Program Planning and Evaluation Committee
    - Correspondence, General, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 202)
    - January study program promotion materials, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 203)
    - Meeting minutes, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 204)
    - Memos, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 205)
    - Regionalization proposal, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 206)
    - Reports, undated (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - Resource packet, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 208)
  - Personnel Committee
    - Correspondence, General, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Correspondence of Samuel Kirk re. search for a UCM secretary for communications, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Job descriptions and assignments, 1965-1968 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Meeting minutes and memos of Henry Bucher, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - NCCCUSA memos, salary sheets, personnel policy handbooks, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Structure of the UCM staff includes report on UCM personnel, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Nominations Committee
    - Biographical data, memos, recommendations, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Meeting attendance and region staff charts, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Nomination and reaction forms, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Nomination forms for officers and General Committee members, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Nomination forms for officers and General Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Nomination forms for officers and General Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 91)
- Program Records, Series II
  - Field Service Committee
    - Administrative records
      - Article "Field Staff Lifeline to Movement" by Len Clough in Wind and Chaff, 1966 November (Box 7, Folder 92)
      - Campus Organizer's packet (incomplete), 1969 (Box 7, Folder 93)
      - Campus Organizer's weekly letters, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      - Carbon copies of Henry Bucher's letters re. China, Latin America, and Migrant Workers, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 95)
      - Concerns: Civil Rights, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 96)
      - Concerns: Labor, 1966, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      - Correspondence, American Friends Service Committee, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 98)
      - Correspondence, Canadian Student Christian Movement, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 99)
      - Correspondence, Hanson, Eileen, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 100)
      - Correspondence, re. Peace Corp including The Peace Corp pamphlet and Peace Corp Fact Book, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      - Correspondence, re. Dick Talbot as part time field staff, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 102)
      - Correspondence, re. Ecumenical Voluntary Service including meeting minutes from CEVSP, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Correspondence, General, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 104)
      - Correspondence, General, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 105)
      - Correspondence, re. Maureen Raphael and Jon C. Jenkins UCM presentation at a LSAA conference, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 106)
      - Correspondence, re. search for the next International Travel Associate, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 107)
      - Correspondence, re. Washington Community Renewal Project, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 108)
      - Correspondence, Yasutake, Michael S. (Co-chairman of Field Services Committee), 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 109)
      - Correspondence, re. Christian Action Movement at DePauw University, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 110)
      - Correspondence, General, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 111)
      - Correspondence, Joint Recruitment for Action in Mission, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 112)
      - Correspondence, Mainor, Thomas F., 1967 (Box 8, Folder 113)
      - Correspondence, Radical Education Project, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 114)
      - Correspondence, re. savings account at Newbury Institution for Savings, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 115)
      - Correspondence, re. annual assembly, 1968 June (Box 8, Folder 116)
      - Correspondence, re. Campus Organizers, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 117)
      - Correspondence, re. Insurance for field Staff, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 118)
      - Correspondence, Kruskop, Kim, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 119)
      - Correspondence, Small, Bunny, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 120)
      - Correspondence, re. hiring and training of campus organizers, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 121)
      - Document mailings to field staff. Includes bibliographies, brochure on Radical Education Project, and various ordering forms for books and tapes, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 122)
      - Field staff proposals not accepted--Ed Hamlett, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 123)
      - Field staff proposals not accepted--miscellaneous, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 124)
      - Field staff proposals not accepted--miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 125)
      - Field staff did not accept--George Brosi, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 126)
      - Field staff did not accept--Tim Correll, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 127)
      - Field staff proposals, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 128)
      - Letters and memos to campus travelers, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 129)
      - Meeting agendas and drafts of minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 130)
      - Meeting minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 131)
      - Memos, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 132)
      - Memos, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 133)
      - Miscellaneous articles, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 134)
      - Miscellaneous materials, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 135)
      - Morris County Citizenship Project, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 136)
      - New Left includes report on Students For a Democratic Society National Convention, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 137)
      - Papers including "Ecumenical Voluntary Service--Models from Life of the University Christian Movement", 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 138)
      - Possible summer projects, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 139)
      - Reports from field staff, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 140)
      - Reports from Henry Bucher, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 141)
      - Report on January study project: New York, Boston, Chicago, San Francisco, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 142)
      - Reports from Organizers, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 143)
      - Report mailings, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 144)
      - Reports "The Nitty Gritty on the Field Staff", 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 145)
      - Reports to write: Bowling Green University, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 146)
      - Resource materials re. racism including Institutional Racism in American Society: a Primer, Readings for Whites on Racism in Amererica: a Selective Bibliography, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 147)